<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2018-03-09T21:08:48+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Joseph Hamilton - Solution Oriented Data Scientist</title><subtitle>A website by and for Joseph Hamilton. A place to explore projects and pursuits, to chase curiosities and catch dreams.
</subtitle><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Project Fletcher Closing</title><link href="/project/fletcher/2018/03/09/Project-Fletcher-Closing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Fletcher Closing" /><published>2018-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/fletcher/2018/03/09/Project-Fletcher-Closing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/fletcher/2018/03/09/Project-Fletcher-Closing/">&lt;p&gt;Project Fletcher is coming to a close…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m on the train commuting down to Project Presentation Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have just been reminded of an significant risk I’ve been running - I’m incredibly dependent upon
access to the Internet to give my presentations.  It’s not just something like developing a presentation
in Google Slides or Slides.com and never downloading an offline copy.  My presentations are live.
They are run from a local web server (on the laptop).  Although I keep trying to ensure all javascript
libraries are served locally, I’m not catching everything.  In a more perfect world, I would/should
have a completely static copy in some format or another as a backup or failsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things seem to work… more or less… eventually.  But it sometimes requires reloading, kicking it, waiting.
I CAN reload the presentation now on the train with no internet access.  Not quite what I’d want while
under a strict time constraint.  Next, I need to make a note to check into something else.  I’ve now got
half a dozen slides or more with iframes pulling other pages.  Somehow, for some reason, these seem to be
falling out of cache.  Sigh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble with these projects is that you are SUPPOSED to stop your exploration, your analysis, etc.,
and then have time focused just on creation and refining the presentation.  But most of us keep at it.
Sometimes, you’re really close to finishing something and once you’ve got it then that opens up a floodgate
of further analysis or insight… sometimes invalidating or overtuning previous ideas or observations
you’d baked into the presentation.  It’s a very weird thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, this is a one of the most key benefits of this bootcamp.  We’re learning time management
and prioritization skills relative to projects overall.  We’re being forced to turning things around in
an iterative fashion where we can present things at various stages along the way.  This is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project Fletcher is coming to a close…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootcamp - Live Programming</title><link href="/metis/2018/03/08/Bootcamp-Live-Programming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootcamp - Live Programming" /><published>2018-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/03/08/Bootcamp-Live-Programming</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/03/08/Bootcamp-Live-Programming/">&lt;p&gt;Pair Programming has given way to Live Programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair Programming is a key part of the daily routine in the Metis Data Science Bootcamp.  Almost every day begins with
approximately half-an-hour devoted to it.  About the only exception to this is any day devoted to Project
presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we &lt;strong&gt;DO&lt;/strong&gt; for Pair Programming varies quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;FEELS&lt;/strong&gt; almost as if they set things up to catch you off guard.  We’ll go days with what are essentially
your standard programming tutorial challenges.  Little coding challenges you can find on any website you could
use to help you learn programming.  The thing here is that once you’ve seen a good number of these, they sort
of stick in your memory and you can just draw upon that to make things work.  And since you’re in a &lt;strong&gt;pair&lt;/strong&gt;,
there’s a reasonably good chance one of you can remember what to do.  Then all of a sudden, out of the blue,
we get a challenge to code one of the algorithms we use for regression or modeling entirely from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common variant is challenges which are really just walkthroughs.  These are actually harder than they
seem because of the time constraint.  I quite often come nowhere near finishing those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we’ve finally switched` to “Live Programming”.  Rarely Pair Programming has been Solo.  Sometimes they do
want to ensure you can do it on your own.  Well, Live Programming is entirely Solo… sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens is someone is picked (supposedly) at random.  I say supposedly because it seemed very coincidental
I got selected immediately after asking whether the sampling was with replacement.  Kendall, who was selected
yesterday responded with a vehement NO.  This person who was selected must go up front and hook up their laptop
to the projector.  Between that and the white board, they respond to a challenge given by the instructors.
Everyone else must work on the same challenge… solo and in silence.  The person on the hot seat, can ask
question, of course.  But nobody else can and everyone else cannot comment on the work of the one in the
hot seat, neither to criticize, correct nor congratulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I daresay, if the last two days are anything to go on, we do much better when we’re not the one up front.
My solution when Kendall was up front was good.  My solution when I went up front was OK.  But Nate had a
better solution.  He was somewhat shy about it but Alice pushed him to go up and show off his solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re all used to going up and presenting after Pair Programming.  That’s usually how Pair Programming
sessions end.  Times up and anyone who has a working solution can go up and present.  Then anyone else
who had a solution significantly different can go up and also present.  So we’re used to presenting
&lt;strong&gt;AFTER&lt;/strong&gt; coding.  It’s presenting &lt;strong&gt;WHILE&lt;/strong&gt; coding that’s the new thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all supposed to work to prepare us for all kinds of coding interview experiences.  We get feedback
from the instructors afterwards.  And sometimes, the instructors change the request or objective of the
challenge on the fly while you’re in progress.  They’re much more focused on your behavior than they
are the specific techniques.  For example, I got a little guidance on legible variable names (actually
sliding constants into variables named descriptively).  But I got called out specifically and majorly
for two behavioral issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t make use of the white board despite Alice suggesting I could.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t pseudo-code first.  A bit later on I started using comments in a pseudo-code like way.
But I should have started with pseudo-code first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback isn’t all negative.  Overall they were pleased with my performance.  I did talk a fair
amount during the process (though I got quiet when wrestling with something in my head - something
that should have been whiteboarded).  They liked that I tested my functions quickly and repeatedly
while developing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being on the hot seat adds a bit of pressure and discomfort for a lot of us.  That’s why, of course,
we’re getting the practice.  It clouds your mind a bit.  For example, yesterday Kendall chose an approach
based on strings.  I used math instead.  Many of these could be done a number of ways.  But Kendall has
a strong Math background.  So I was surprised she chose strings.  When you’re up front, you tend to get
tunnel vision.  That’s part of why we need the practice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Pair Programming has given way to Live Programming.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Fletcher Began</title><link href="/project/fletcher/2018/03/01/Project-Fletcher-Began/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Fletcher Began" /><published>2018-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/fletcher/2018/03/01/Project-Fletcher-Began</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/fletcher/2018/03/01/Project-Fletcher-Began/">&lt;p&gt;Project Fletcher began a while ago…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess you might say as far as blogging goes, the cat caught my tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not yet finished blogging about Project McNulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is hilarious because the storytelling part about that project was that some
nefarious group imprisoned my blog.  Lo and behold if that didn’t happen in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often see graduates from previous cohorts milling around the Metis campus.
It seems very worthwhile to see what they’re up to or to ask them about their
experiences.  A fair amount of the time, they’re working with Ashley.  Some times,
they’re just coming in on a regular, if infrequent, basis and they spend their
time working on some skill or another.  But one high runner for activities is
polishing up their past projects either in their blog or in their GitHub repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heavens, if I’ve not created the same problem for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was behind on the last project due to planned and unplanned absences.  The instructors
gave me a grace day and I presented a day after everyone else.  They were also understanding
in the sense that they didn’t expect or require me to submit or publish my material on the
same schedule as everyone else.  But I didn’t realize they weren’t going to wait for that
to grade my work.  I’m not surprised.  They make the rounds almost every day to check up
on our progress.  Between that and us pestering them, they have a good sense of what we’re
doing.  That and the presentation itself is a good metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the trouble was that my lag on ending Project Three meant I was already bleeding
into the time where everyone else was working on Project Four.  And if that wasn’t enough
I have started my research and work leading to my next Investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus is wildly split now.  And Project Three is the only thing where there’s no real pressure.
The others have deadlines.  Nonetheless, there’s one thing I wish to do before I publish Project
Three… so it’s gonna linger for a bit…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Project Four is NLP and Unsupervised Learning, both of which can be… umm… a
tad weird.  I chose two optional scopes for the project.  We each had a private meeting with
the instructors to go over these.  Yet again, I found myself with an incorrect assessment of
which would be harder.  I knew which would be more direct and in line with the lectures, etc.
But it’s not just that the other would be a bit harder… apparently it would have been much
more difficult in the time frame available.  In my scope review meeting with the instructors, I
asked about how we would measure success for this project.  The previous two projects had various
metrics.  The response was interesting…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When you have something that makes sense.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… a bit of experimentation with Topic Modeling, and I have a much deeper appreciation for
that statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another intriguing aspect of this project is that I may actually take advantage of the AWS servers.
I may not truly need such if I limit my scope.  But to scale up, it seems very likely I’ll actually
benefit.  I don’t need an EC2 instance for MongoDB.  I just dumped stuff to my local MongoDB server
I had running since Project Two.  But, I may need some extra horsepower.  We’ll have to see what I
can accomplish…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project Fletcher began a while ago…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finished SQL on HackerRank</title><link href="/hackerrank/2018/02/24/Finished-SQL-on-HackerRank/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finished SQL on HackerRank" /><published>2018-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/hackerrank/2018/02/24/Finished-SQL-on-HackerRank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/hackerrank/2018/02/24/Finished-SQL-on-HackerRank/">&lt;p&gt;Yay!!  I finally finished the SQL track on HackerRank!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Three of the Metis Bootcamp had three areas of focus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SQL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Visualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spun up EC2 instances on AWS to serve as database servers using Postgres.  I confirmed that past the lectures I didn’t
need to stick with that for the requirements of the Project.  That is to say, I could stick with a local server.  This was
my preference and will be for the next project as well which requires the use of MongoDB.  I used MongoDB locally for Project
Two.  So I see no reason to switch to AWS for Project Four.  I DID follow along the lecture and exercise to prove in the
functionality of using the AWS instance.  But I’m not going to bother for any project until I can see a benefit of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I’ve been thinking about that.  Alice says for the most part Data Scientists aren’t simultaneously Data Engineers.
Usually, we’ll not be &lt;strong&gt;creating&lt;/strong&gt; databases.  We’ll be using them.  In that vein, we’ll be using (usually) whatever is
already out there, whatever it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… when does it makes sense for us to actually use these AWS instances over our local machines?  And then, how best
should we use them?  I’m rather curious if it would make better sense for us to run Jupyter or Jupyter Labs on the same
machine running the database server… or alternatively another instance.  To start, we’re using meager, small instances
in the free tiers.  Decent laptops surpass that.  But… maybe just maybe… we could come across something we could
parallelize and then use multiple AWS instances.  Or, possibly, we’d benefit from letting something run for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dunno.  As far as it pertains to processing power, memory or storage, I’ve not yet reached a point where for what
we’re doing I need to switch.  But, I may take advantage of the instances for my next Investigation.  I’ve got some
ideas…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I had hoped or planned to keep my feet wet in HackerRank by maintaining a slow pace of about a challenge
a day.  The track I was working on was the SQL track.  Given the focus on SQL with Project Three, I decided to ramp it
up a bit and try to finish the track.  This worked well enough… until the last challenge in the “Advanced Join”
category.  That was my final challenge for the whole track.  It was marked “Hard” and had a lower completion score
than the others (meaning fewer people who’d ever attempted it eventually succeeded).  I was determined NOT to look
to the Discussions for help.  I lost several hours on it before abandoning it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t touch HackerRank after that because the work for Project Three and the Challenge Sets had buried me.
HackerRank got lonely and sent me an email suggesting that I work on that very challenge.  Chuckle…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… the SQL Challenge Set from Metis gave me lots of relevant practice.  This Challenge Set was broken into
four sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SQL via a tutorial website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SQL via a Python SQLAlchemy interface to a Postgres database&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SQLite&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SQL with a Postgres database directly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hilariously, I completely missed the requirement of SQLAlchemy for that second part till the last challenge.  I was indeed
using the sqlalchemy module, but only to get a connection with which I was simply pumping in raw SQL.  The last challenge
made a remark about what you’d have to do because SQLAlchemy didn’t support a particular functionality.  This made no sense
to me until it dawned on me what I was supposed to have been doing all along.  Sigh… So I had to back up and redo the
entire section.  This was a huge blessing though.  It very much helped to already have SQL that worked so I could
“translate” to the way SQLAlchmey works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… Project Three is largely done.  I still have a bit of work to “publish” it.  But as somewhat of a diversion, a bit
of a cooldown, or just to wrap up loose ends, I decided to finish that track on HackerRank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a small database to replicate the sample shown in the project description and fired up a Jupyter notebook to
hammer away at it.  I finally got it working!!  I thought I’d have to use a bit of recursion, but that proved unnecessary.
I just had to carefully construct enough WITH clauses to get the job done.  Ironically, PostgreSQL is not supported by
HackerRank.  So I chose Oracle and then had to “translate”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All done!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="SQL" /><summary type="html">Yay!! I finally finished the SQL track on HackerRank!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tired… so… tired…</title><link href="/metis/2018/02/22/Tired-So-Tired/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tired... so... tired..." /><published>2018-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/02/22/Tired-So-Tired</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/02/22/Tired-So-Tired/">&lt;p&gt;I am incredibly tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have reached another milestone in the Bootcamp.  We have finished Project Three and have begun Project Four.
Everyone else gave their presentation for Project Three yesterday and I wrapped it up by presenting mine
this morning.  There is an interesting segue between projects where folk wrap up their work for submission,
which includes “publishing” their presentation along with pertinent code, etc., and then the brainstorming
for the next project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was out for a planned absence Monday and then I got sick.  It was something similar to stomach flu, food
poisoning or possibly I weak case of the flu (which is possible since I did get the shot a few weeks ago).
The illness had a greater impact due to the fact I needed the rest and quite literally couldn’t maintain
focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to work over the weekend and was the first to submit the last &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt; Challenge Set.  We’re
still getting a couple challenge sets a week.  But from here on out, they’re all optional.  And, again, the
prioritization is Projects first, Blog second, Challenges next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what I &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; be doing right now is Project.  I have to publish my stuff.  So… why am I blogging
instead?  Well… because I’m fried.  I’m not the only one, of course.  Derrick gave his Investigation
presentation early this afternoon and he warned us he was going to be much more mellow then normal because
he’s so tired.  And Dean was yawning as much as I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot speak for everyone else.  Especially since I wasn’t here this week till Wednesday.  But I get a
feeling many others work just as hard on their projects.  I really do wish I had been here to help my
“team”.  The projects are solo now.  But we’re still grouped into clusters where we’re supposed to keep
tabs on each other, help each other, even represent each other.  Amy channelled me as she imitated me during
the MVP and she was much louder as a result.  I was supposed to be here to help her practice.  I’m not
sure it would have mattered.  But she drifted back to being really quiet during her presentation 
yesterday.  She did good otherwise.  As did Michael.  Michael’s project was on predicting likelihood of
Chicago restaurants failing inspections.  He called out the restaurant we went to for Chinese New Year’s,
which was hilarious since my wife, at least, believes that to be a strong contender for my illness.  I
sort of doubt it since that would have meant a much longer time than usual between bad food and the
onset of symptoms.  But who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was rather intent on getting back Wednesday to see the other presentations.  I learned quite a bit,
not only from what they presented including all their methods and tools but also from the feedback
the instructors gave them.  I was halfway done with my presentation (having stayed up very, very late
the night before) and probably could have winged an incomplete slide show.  But Alice was rather
gracious in giving me an extra day - like they did for Amy who was actually sick the day of presentations
for Project Two.  I knew I needed the time so I took it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I really did need it.  I &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt; stayed up very, very late.  Some of what I was chasing wasn’t
strictly necessary.  But there were a couple of ideas I wanted to explore and have tried out in case
I got any questions pointing in that direction.  I did NOT get around to a working example of using
plotly.js.  And it didn’t help matters that I had to spend some time addressing laptop and virtual
machine issues because one of the (virtual) hard drives for the VM (the one running Postgres… which
I was dependent on for this project) had to be resized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next project is reportedly a very difficult one for students.  We’re shifting from Supervised
Learning to Unsupervised Learning.  And no… this has nothing to do with us being given more freedom.
Many of us used the experience of Project One to guide our choice of what to do for Project Two.
But things are different enough for Project Three that we may not quite be as able to choose wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’m having a ball and learning a ton.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I am incredibly tired.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Chinese New Year!!</title><link href="/metis/2018/02/16/Happy-Chinese-New-Year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Chinese New Year!!" /><published>2018-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/02/16/Happy-Chinese-New-Year</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/02/16/Happy-Chinese-New-Year/">&lt;p&gt;We just had our first Lunch Outing as a Metis cohort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently past cohorts had a longer schedule and a longer official Lunch Break.  When
we really do have the entire afternoon for work on our projects, there’s a fuzzy boundary
between Lunch and Work.  A lot of feedback about ending the day at 6pm has prompted a
change to a normally 9-5 shift with an hour for Lunch.  The flip side of this is that
a lot our Lunches become working Lunches with workshops and stuff squeezed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a long stretch of days where we really weren’t getting to work on our projects
till later in the afternoon.  Between presentations, workshops, reviews and what not,
we were feeling the crunch and pressure.  For most of us, this just shifts the burden
to late evenings/nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong.  These other things are all worthy things.  We &lt;strong&gt;NEED&lt;/strong&gt; the Career
Services and related workshops Ashley provides.  And we all benefit a lot from the
investigation presentations from each other.  The Quiz Review was also beneficial.
I didn’t do too bad on the quiz.  I got greater than 90%.  I teased the instructors
that they should have provided us histograms of the scores or other robust visualizations,
etc.  They did inform us that we didn’t get first place amongst the campuses this year.
Seattle just barely scraped ahead of us!  David and Alice enumerated about a dozen topics
on the whiteboard.  One by one, a student got up to discuss, present or teach that topic.
This proved to be good review and reinforcement, especially for the one presenting.
I &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; chickened out angling for easy topics or those where I had more background.
I ended up with “general questions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was our first day in quite a while with the afternoon purely devoted to personal
project work.  The instructors wander around to check in with folk during this time frame
to assist, guide or cajole folk as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today was a voluntary choice for folk to eat away at time available for project work…
all in good fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dean has been pining for some good Chinese Dim Sum for quite a while.  I thought they’d all
gone after the bowling excursion.  After the bowling a few of us split off to go home
while the rest were planning on going out for dinner.  But apparently they didn’t go to
wherever Dean wanted.  And, to be honest, even the choice of bowling was in opposition
to Dean’s desire.  The group voted between Bowling and Dim Sum and bowling eeked ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s Chinese New Year!!  We have three Chinese: Alice; Dean; Derrick.  So most of
us joined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a picture:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Metis_Outing_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Metis Outing at Minghin Cuisine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">We just had our first Lunch Outing as a Metis cohort.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Going Off The Grid</title><link href="/metis/2018/02/16/Going-Off-The-Grid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going Off The Grid" /><published>2018-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/02/16/Going-Off-The-Grid</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/02/16/Going-Off-The-Grid/">&lt;p&gt;I have a bit of preparation to do…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just after I might have considered myself caught up after finding myself having to work remotely for a couple
of days, I have a pure absence coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A family issue has arisen that has prompted us to take advantage of the fact the kids are off due to
President’s Day.  This is problematic for my experience here at Metis for a couple of reasons.  There will
be a bit of time where I’ll be driving.  But when I’m lucky enough to be a passenger, I might be able to
do stuff on the laptop… but sans the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about this issue early on in the Bootcamp.  David made the comment that the “dirty secret” of the
industry is that, on average, programmers do one websearch for every ten lines of code.  I really believe it.
This isn’t even really a bad thing.  You want to avoid reinventing the wheel.  And you want to be able to
incorporate the discussions or learnings of others rather than repeating all the same mistakes or ignoring
opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve look ahead to challenge sets to ensure I have datasets downloaded, installed or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some things where I can grab documentation.  I just dp.  But I may also have to shift work around so
I can plan on doing certain things when I’ll be off the ownloaded huge PDFs for the documentation 
of scikit learn and matplotlib.  I’m sure these will help.  But I may also have to shift work around so
I can plan on doing certain things when I’ll be off the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just skimming the scikit learn documentation, I confirmed a hunch.  This past week, I subclassed regressors
to create “dummy” or baseline models for comparative purposes.  This was a bit clumsy.  Part of that
was because I only iteratively added functions as I found I needed them.  I knew that surely sklearn had
this already.  But I didn’t bother looking it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a good thing, actually.  This forced me to dig a bit deeper into what &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; be going on
with some of these functions or behaviors between parts of sklearn (estimators, scorers, metrics, etc.).
This is one thing that troubles me a bit with sklearn - it’s too powerful.  It gives you so much functionality
in a standard fashion that you can get addicted to tossing things together without really understanding
what’s going on underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that’s key is avoiding the seduction of working with lots of data.  Sometimes, it’s really
just more important to work with very small datasets.  I don’t mean just for speed of optimizing.  It
is really much clearer to &lt;strong&gt;see&lt;/strong&gt; what’s going on when you only have a few rows and columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I dearly hope I an absence with travel doesn’t prove too costly.  The pressure is on for the
current project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I have a bit of preparation to do…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project McNulty - Choices</title><link href="/project/mcnulty/2018/02/13/Project-McNulty-MVP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project McNulty - Choices" /><published>2018-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/mcnulty/2018/02/13/Project-McNulty-MVP</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/mcnulty/2018/02/13/Project-McNulty-MVP/">&lt;p&gt;Project McNulty has passed MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on Project McNulty has been interesting.  I’ve suffered a bit due to days not being in person for
lectures.  In general, the project has been more straightforward.  Nonetheless, all of our work seems
to require a lot of time - many very late nights.  There is almost always some aspect of what you’re working
on that is new.  So any time saved because you already know one thing is counter-balanced with something
that you haven’t yet mastered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SQL and database stuff isn’t new to me.  But PostgreSQL is.  I’ve known OF Postgres.  But I’ve mainly used
MySQL in the past.  And Postgres isn’t even an option for databases in the SQL track on HackerRank… which
I’ve almost completely finished.  So getting used to weird Postgres quirks is one thing.  Yet another is
learning SQLAlchemy and more important for this particular project Socrata and SODA.  Because of the structure
already inherent in the dataset I was using, I wanted to create and use a function that would use SQLAlchemy
to create the table strcture for Postgres automatically from the Socrata metadata.  What I ended up with
certainly isn’t &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt;.  But it would be very straightforward to pick it up and tailor it for any
future project using another Socrata-based dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Punching the data in was easy once I had the table set up.  After a few tests with very small batches, I
pushed in the entire thing.  It took about 100 seconds for 6.5 million rows.  I still want to go back and
create a function to “top off” my data.  The Chicago Data Portal updates almost daily.  I should be able to
use a SODA query to pull in recent records and upsert to punch it into my local store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next… once I started to &lt;strong&gt;use&lt;/strong&gt; the data, I encountered some common database sorts of problems.  Queries
were slow.  So I punched in a few indices.  That helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that I have a number of issues related to size.  First, I can exhaust memory.  Any number of things
are holding onto or leaking memory.  Rebooting the VM helps.  But overall, I’ve set the VM at 10G.  I
&lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; update the laptop to 32G and give the VM 25G.  But that’s expensive.  Alternatively, I can set
up swap files.  The best for speed is the SSD.  But I don’t want to eat into that space and upgrading the
SSD wouldn’t just be costly - it’d be painful and risky.  The HD has plenty of space but it’s slow.  So
as an alternative I ordered a slim USB3 stick.  Using it for swap will likely kill it.  Oh well.  I’ll be
free from “out-of-memory” issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory issues are just one part of the size problem.  Time is another.  But today we covered spare matrices
in lecture.  I have several large categoricals.  When I blow those out to dummy variables I get huge things
that take a lot of time.  I &lt;strong&gt;NEED&lt;/strong&gt; to employ sparse matrices here for this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond what efforts I will undertake to setup swap for a large amount of virtual memory and tricks
to speed things up, now that I’ve gotten a couple pretty pictures based on prototypes for the MVP, I
also just need to play more with much smaller datasets.  For the MVP, I just queried for all of the data
for 2017.  Even that was a quarter million records.  For model evaluation, I do need something that captures
a fair representation of the categoricals.  But nothing so big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t bother with interpretability or descriptions of the modeling… at all for the MVP.  I just described
the dataset, tossed in a geo picture I created via Tableau and showed a couple of learning curves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good enough for MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… what was &lt;strong&gt;VERY INTERESTING&lt;/strong&gt; for the Project McNulty MVP was that we did not present our MVPs.  Project
Three is actually a solo project.  But we were grouped into teams.  Our teams are like “project buddies” where
we each go to our team for assistance and help before others or the instructors.  The real fun here, however,
was that someone else on our team presented our MVP on our behalf.  This meant we had to communicate with
each other well enough that we could give the teammate’s presentation.  The way this was explained early on
was that we’d have to understand each other’s code.  But that wasn’t truly necessary.  It &lt;strong&gt;WAS&lt;/strong&gt; if that
team presented via the work in a Juptyer notebook which several did.  A slide presentation of any kind
negated that need.  And for the final presentation we’re back to giving our own talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… now we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have simply acted as if we were presenting the talk on our teammate’s behalf… you know…
which we were doing.  But no… the first person that went up started by acting as if they were the other
person.  And it just got more hilarious from there.  Everyone followed that trend of pretending to be the
other person.  Then people started trying to do a good job &lt;strong&gt;imitating&lt;/strong&gt; the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got utterly comical at that point.  Now, for some things the instructor’s questions were fielded by the
actual author.  Alex got into it with David because David questioned whether he was really using “Accuracy”
as the metric to compare models.  Alex retorted that he was only using Accuracy because the things he had
ready to go to create charts used Accuracy.  I exclaimed “ditto” because I knew I had the very same issue.
But… when it was my turn, Amy (who was presented on my behalf) and I started speaking together.  So,
I deferred to let “Joseph” respond.  And Amy was hilarious since she just bluffed her way through saying,
in essence, that for the most part all of these metrics trend together and any one of them would do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was silly, but incredibly funny.  On a more serious note, this highlighted something I’d missed not
being here for a couple days.  I scoured the material again to confirm “logloss” wasn’t covered.  It seems
it was something David covered from material on his own blog.  I need to go read that… especially since
it is probably important for my project.  Not only was it not in the material.  It wasn’t in the challenge sets and we haven’t
yet covered it in a Pair Problem.  But after the David-Amy exchange, David all but insinuated it
may well be in an upcoming Pair Problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… while the others were going, Amy was clearly getting into the spirit of all this and she asked me
to imitate myself so she could work from that.  I told here that was silly.  Imitate myself?  Preposterous.
In any case, she did a fair job imitating me… I guess.  One obvious thing it did was it made her present
loudly.  She’s normally as quiet as a mouse and gets even quieter as she continues to speak.  I imagine I’m
at the other end… just a loud presenter.  Well… it get her more where she needs to be.  I don’t think I
did anywhere near as good a job channeling Michael.  And although Michael may have somewhat started with
an Amy imitation, I don’t think he kept it up long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more hilarity followed as Adam imitated Derrick.  But the really memorable thing was a comment Adam
made when Derrick got done presenting for Tiffany and Tiffany went up to present for Adam.  Adam whined
that now Tiffany finally knew what it felt like to follow Tiffany.  We all lost it.  Several students
have, in the past, overtly requested from the instructors that they be able to present before Tiffany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?  Tiffany’s past work experience has drilled into her the use of Keynote and Tableau in a way that
is very fine.  She’s mentioned a previous boss was very finicky on the use of Keynote.  Things had to
look “good”.  It’s not that we cannot do so… given time… lots of time…  It’s that no matter what
we do, it is upstaged by Tiffany who seems not to even be trying.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project McNulty has passed MVP.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Snow Strikes</title><link href="/metis/2018/02/10/Snow-Strikes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Snow Strikes" /><published>2018-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/02/10/Snow-Strikes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/02/10/Snow-Strikes/">&lt;p&gt;La Nina winters have returned…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dunno about you, but with regards to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Ni%C3%B1o%E2%80%93Southern_Oscillation&quot;&gt;ENSO&lt;/a&gt;,
I kinda prefer the El Niño years.  The cyclones are “over there” in the Pacific and the winters tend to be dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between flu seasons and snow season, if you’re someone considering the Metis Bootcamp, I might suggest you
avoid the winter season.  Of course, if you &lt;strong&gt;ARE&lt;/strong&gt; such a person, might I suggest you list me as one who recommended
you to Metis?  Chuckle…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I was “remote” Wednesday and Thursday this week due to kids down with the flu.  Then &lt;strong&gt;EVERYONE&lt;/strong&gt; was
remote Friday since the Metis Chicago campus was closed due to the Winter Storm..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bizarrely, the Pair Programming schedule aligned with this.  We have an odd number in the cohort.  So as “pairs” go,
there is always a leftover.  That individual can work solo or they can join any other pair of their choice.  I dutifully
got in front of my computer Wednesday morning before 9am to identify my pair partner only to find I had none.  Then
I looked at the assignment for the day…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK.  I have to pause a bit and opine a bit about Pair Programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re past the initial weirdness where we didn’t know each other and where egos may have come into play.  Sure, some
are more amenable to working with others.  But we’re all in this together.  So, my thoughts of the moment don’t have
to do with that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No… it’s the nature of the assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual assignments range pretty widely in their difficulty level, their topic, their scope, etc.  A lot of the
time, they have a “trivial” feel to them.  Of course, what’s trivial to one may be novel to another.  But you get a
sense these are standard teaching exercises or refreshers.  And then one comes out of the blue to spank you hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this week…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monday - SQL exercises (yawn.. refresher)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tuesday - &lt;strong&gt;standard&lt;/strong&gt; simple recursion examples.  So standard, in fact, that Amy took one look at it and was
entirely ready to &lt;em&gt;teach&lt;/em&gt; the lesson of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memoization&quot;&gt;memoization&lt;/a&gt; because this
particular examples was &lt;strong&gt;THE&lt;/strong&gt; “go to” example for that topic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wednesday - Program Batch Gradient Descent from Scratch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thursday  - Finish Wednesday’s work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Friday - Run through an entire classification exercise with charts and logistic regression of 6 features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do ya see a difference there?!?  If not just follow along…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being “off” Wednesday and Thursday underscored the difference between reading the material and being in a group
setting where you can rattle off questions immediately to the instructors.  Furthermore there is a clear structure between:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reading about certain techniques&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementing projects using said techniques&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running through a complete exercise using said techniques in less than 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I had one &lt;strong&gt;HUGE&lt;/strong&gt; advantage over my peers on Wednesday.  They all had to move on once the 30 minutes were up.
I had no such restriction.  They didn’t fire up Zoom or anything for me.  I was just connected via Slack in a loose
fashion with the curriculum and such available for me to read at my pace.  So the only thing that hindered me from
completing the task was my caretaker duties at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… on that note… if I can program Batch Gradient Descent from scratch while enduring the fingernails-on-chalkboard
sensation of a teenage daughter whimpering and moaning while fighting off a high fever, I imagine I can endure the
pressure of Code Interviews.  Mind you, if you’re a prospective employer, might I suggest you peruse my work on
HackerRank, GitHub, these projects, etc., and spare me said ordeal.  But I’m better prepared nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, working with Gradient Descent was interesting because you had to determine things were failing because
your code was bad or because your choice of alpha was way off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t even realize the plan was to continue Thursday till I again dutifully checked before 9am to see the assignment.
Apparently, even then, only a couple pairs had working examples.  I’d pat myself on the back except that it’d be an
unfair comparison.  Sure I got it working… but not in two 30 minute sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday was much more fun because the entire class was remote.  This made things interesting because of how everyone
chose to work together.  Several of us had issues with one platform or another.  Nate, my pair partner, immediately
suggested we stick to nothing more than Slack.  This meant no voice.  So, actually, we were both just working the
problem independently, simultaneously while peppering each other with questions or comments.  I was surprised how
far I got actually, but there was a strong sense that I was “behind” on the material due to missing lectures.
Once the entire class joined via Zoom for review, it became clear our choice was sound.  Far too many others wasted
too much of their time fighting with getting “connected”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also hilarious to see everyone in their “natural” setting.  I must say it seemed several of the students hadn’t
really even gotten out of bed yet!  We got introduced to a number of pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple lectures and a bit of slacking teammates on project work, I had to take the “lunch break” to go out and
shovel snow.  I just barely finished in time to come back in for a Metis-wide quiz.  All four campuses were taking
this quiz at roughly the same time.  It was declared to be a closed-book quiz.  Of course, it’s all on our honor,
especially since we (in Chicago) were all remote.  But the entire idea is to assess ourselves, both on an individual
level and on the levels of each campus and the curriculum/teaching overall.  So why bother cheating?!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had an hour allocated to the quiz.  But I burned through it fairly quickly because for most of it you either knew
it or you didn’t.  There wasn’t much middle ground.  Almost none of it struck me as something I’d never heard of.
It wasn’t that kind of “not knowing”.  It was more like, oh yeah… that topic… that I’d not yet had the chance to
review properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were still a few things where I sort of understood the general idea but hadn’t yet solidified on &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; term
meant &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; thing.  So I did slow down and methodically work through my reasoning so at the very least my answers
demonstrated a consistent thinking, even if consistently wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I’m having a ball, but I’m “at risk” of slipping behind.  It’s tough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">La Nina winters have returned…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project McNulty - Choices</title><link href="/project/mcnulty/2018/02/08/Project-McNulty-Choices/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project McNulty - Choices" /><published>2018-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/mcnulty/2018/02/08/Project-McNulty-Choices</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/mcnulty/2018/02/08/Project-McNulty-Choices/">&lt;p&gt;Project McNulty - what to do…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve chosen two scopes.  But I do have to select one for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have approached this project with a bit more caution.  I don’t want to be “chasing ghosts”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, of course, part of this overall experience is to develop the skill of storytelling, even
when there really doesn’t seem to be much of a story to tell.  But, it’s a lot more fun
if there is something there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to be able  to pivot to the second choice rather seemlessly if needed, as needed.
So, in that vein, I performed a bit of Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) for both my scope choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to proceed with the Chicago Crime Scene scope.  However, time permitting, I will
continue to work on the other one.  Where it’s “simple”, this ought to be straightforward.  For
example, it shouldn’t be more work to cram that data into Postgresql once I’m able to do that for
the first scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the EDA Notebooks for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/joseph-r-hamilton/Project_McNulty/blob/master/Exploration/Assessment_Crime.ipynb&quot;&gt;The Chicago Crime Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/joseph-r-hamilton/Project_McNulty/blob/master/Exploration/Assessment_Music.ipynb&quot;&gt;A Music Genre Detector&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project McNulty - what to do…</summary></entry></feed>