<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2018-01-10T20:23:55+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Joseph Hamilton - Solution Oriented Data Scientist</title><subtitle>A website by and for Joseph Hamilton. A place to explore projects and pursuits, to chase curiosities and catch dreams.
</subtitle><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Dry Run Report</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dry Run Report" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report/">&lt;p&gt;I have journeyed to downtown Chicago today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be joining the 2018 Winter Cohort of the Metis Data Science Bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual activities begin next Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seemed very prudent to make a number of dry run commutes to work out the kinks.  I’ve been collaborating with Metis for a couple months now
in the sense that I’ve been coming to their facility for a number of meetups and events.  For all of that I simply drove.  Driving to/from Chicago
in rush hour times is a rather undesirable task, but the real kicker is the expense for parking.  To pay the evening rate for an evening meetup is
a lot different than paying every day for a full day’s parking.  In a real sense a car in downtown Chicago is a liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually came down last Friday.  I made that a leisurely affair.  I left shortly before noon.  I brought my young son… who actually helped because he was familiar with mini-DisplayPort adapters.  I haven’t needed to use that sort of connector between laptops and monitors before.  After an our or so playing around with basics of hooking up to the network and external monitors and whatnot, we returned.  Again, it was at our leisure.  We popped into a number of stores along the way back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m trying to match real times.  And (as I kind of expected) I missed my train.  It took a lot longer to find parking at the train station which was also a lot further away.  I thought it was far away last time.  Sheesh!!  But that’s why I’m doing these dry runs.  Nathan, the Metis Chicago Program Manager informs me this cohort will be changing the schedule a bit.  So Friday, I’ll actually take a different train and attempt to get get here by 9am.  Nobody may be here.  Again, there’s no reason for anyone to be here at the moment.  But if so, I’ll just pop on over to UIC and work from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve plopped myself down at a workstation.  I may pick up an adapter to be able to use more than one external monitor.  I’ll be continuing work on the blog and the MOOC I’m pursuing… at least till Nathan boots me out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I have journeyed to downtown Chicago today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog Enhancements</title><link href="/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog Enhancements" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements/">&lt;p&gt;I took a brief pause between the first and second courses in this Harvard series to take another look
at a couple of things.  One of the things I need to wrestle with quickly is how to handle projects on
this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I’m using the HydeJack theme.  I could upgrade to the Pro version to get some additional
support for projects.  But I’m not certain I want that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went off on a journey on the web to see how others are using Hydejack or Jekyll in general for projects.
I found a ton of orphaned sites.  Lots of people seem to be starting or barely starting blogs and then
abandoning them.  I may have said earlier, but I find this blog is actually primarily for &lt;strong&gt;ME&lt;/strong&gt;.  If
others are reading this, that’s great.  And this does serve as a bit of a showcase.  But I know from
experience the value of being able to look backwards at logs, journals, etc., of your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I’ve also found very little really effective use of these project sections, tabs, pages or whatnot.
But I did find a few.  So I have to ponder what I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also reminded I need to go back and fluff out tags and categories.  They end up a bit “messy” in
the site layout if I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also reviewed the blogs created by the 2017 Fall Cohort of the Metis Bootcamp.  These were &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt;
project-centric actually.  Maybe I’m just chatty.  But again, experience has taught me that it’s actually
very valuable to be able to look backwards after several months and years to see exactly what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there really does seem to be a fairly consistent pattern here of portraying projects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a front-page of sorts which either uses a picture and one-liner for each project as a link to a more robust page for that project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each project is summarized as a single page which is essentially a summary of the overall project with a focus on the results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some pages includes links to the previous and next projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some folk used the blog as their mechanism to portray their projects.  But then the blog served almost no other purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what do I want?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at some of the better examples I’ve found using Hydejack Pro…  I found one that rather easily
incorporated links between the (single) post and the project page.  I could do almost the same thing using
a dedicated category page.  In the interest of time, I probably should just upgrade.  I likely won’t take
advantage of everything in Pro.  I’ve found an “Intro” I like better.  I only hesitate because I’d probably
benefit more from building my own stuff in Jekyll.  But I know full well that could eat up a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to move quickly here.  Before the Metis Bootcamp starts, I would like to have back-created a page and some posts related to a project I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time passes…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK.  I’m now halfway through the second course and taking some time to work on the blog.  For the purpose
of working in the project functionality, I elevated the previous post on SwirlyPy to a project.  I &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; hope to
keep working on that till it works well enough to serve my needs and help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chasing this I found some eye-candy I also want.  But… I’ve reached a point where I have what I want with
regards to the project pages connecting to and from the related blog posts.  So, I’m pushing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Projects" /><summary type="html">I took a brief pause between the first and second courses in this Harvard series to take another look at a couple of things. One of the things I need to wrestle with quickly is how to handle projects on this blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stats Series - Course Two Halfway Point</title><link href="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/09/Course-Two-Halfway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stats Series - Course Two Halfway Point" /><published>2018-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/09/Course-Two-Halfway</id><content type="html" xml:base="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/09/Course-Two-Halfway/">&lt;p&gt;Just concluded Week 2 of 4!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had followed recommendations to this Harvard series when looking for some coursework on Linear Algebra.
That’s this second course in this series.  I chose to back up and do the first course beforehand.  That
was more prudent than I’d thought.  I actually needed that first course as a refresher for Stats more than
I need this.  Furthermore, that first course covers things such as Data Visualization and Data Exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m breezing through this second course for a few reasons.  First, the actual work is similar enough to
what I’d been doing earlier on HackerRank.  So the mechanics are easier.  I’m getting better practice
doing things different ways.  But it’s not the same as figuring out matplotlib stuff trying to do the
same thing in R and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had, at the moment, to summarize the differences between R and Python, it’d be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REMEMBER&lt;/strong&gt; R is 1-based, Python is 0-based&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything in Python is backwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, even within Python you have to be careful.  Does that columns of ones in my coeefficient matrix go on
the right or on the left?  That may depend on what module or function you’re using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I still have a lingering feeling I need to go out and find a raw Linear Algebra refresher.
This course is very tailored towards how to use Linear Algebra for the purpose of statistics.  That’s
good for what I’m doing at the moment though.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><category term="Harvard" /><category term="R" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Jupyter" /><summary type="html">Just concluded Week 2 of 4!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stats Series - First Course Done</title><link href="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/06/First-Stats-Course-Down/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stats Series - First Course Done" /><published>2018-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/06/First-Stats-Course-Down</id><content type="html" xml:base="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/06/First-Stats-Course-Down/">&lt;p&gt;Wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;strong&gt;DONE&lt;/strong&gt; with the first course: Statistics and R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no significant problem mirroring the entire coursework in R and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… I learned to be wary of the Python module that lets you directly interface to R.  Oh it &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt; well enough.  Well… it works great in Spyder and Jupyter since the paths are all set up via Anaconda.  I’ve not gotten Rodeo to agree where R is.  But… there are some interesting oddities when trying to convert the data sets available innately in R.  It doesn’t always do what you expect.  To be safe, it’s often better just to dump it to CSV and read it back in from Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to move on to the second course: Introduction to Linear Models and Matrix Algebra.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><category term="Harvard" /><category term="R" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Spyder" /><category term="Rodeo" /><category term="Jupyter" /><summary type="html">Wow!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy New Year</title><link href="/blog/2018/01/01/Happy-New-Year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year" /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2018/01/01/Happy-New-Year</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2018/01/01/Happy-New-Year/">&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A LOT is changing for me this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in the midst of a career transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am agressively pursuing training in a variety of forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may end up sliding into working contracts as a Consultant either in place of or in addition to traditional employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was reminded today that you have to be prepared.  Specifically, you have to be prepared for when your machines and data fail… which means you have to have a backup plan.  It probably also would be wise for me to reboot more often… at least to be sure things will reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Linux Virtual Machine I’m using for my MOOC studies and Data Science work went belly up.  It was the weirdest thing.  But it was a wonderful object lesson to be careful about how you interpret data.  What one could &lt;strong&gt;SEE&lt;/strong&gt; seemed to be odd errors mostly related to networking when it seemed to fail booting.  Playing with the NIC didn’t do anything.  Only when I booted from a (virtual) DVD-ROM and chrooted into drive to check the logs did I find out what the problem really was… and that the system had indeed booted, complete with networking.  What had failed was SDDM.  Somehow SDDM had gotten updated without a dependency.  A full system upgrade and all was fine…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good reminder I need a robust recovery plan for my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s my task for the moment.  I’m setting up rsnapshot which will facilitate recovering from my own mistakes.  And I’ll be implementing a cloud backup as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Backup" /><summary type="html">Happy New Year!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stats Series - Progress</title><link href="/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/28/Stats-Series-Progress/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stats Series - Progress" /><published>2017-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/28/Stats-Series-Progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/28/Stats-Series-Progress/">&lt;p&gt;Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfway through the first course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;IS&lt;/strong&gt; taking a bit more time to push through this mirroring things in Python.  But this is proving to be invaluable.  For many things, doing it twice permits me to notice, catch and fix errors.  I’m also using the IDEs to prototype things and Jupyter notebooks more for the ultimate presentation.  This is building for me a library of notebooks for quick reference of how to do particular tasks as well as parallels between R and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using Spyder rather than Rodeo.  I plan to switch for the second half of this first course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have had real problem so far replicating everything in Python, including all the related plots, there is no easy way to make the respective random number generators behave the same way.  I can set seeds for both to keep answers consistent in both.  But they rarely match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing this helps is forcing me to reflect more on understanding what’s really going on rather than just relying on functions and formulae.  There’s an enormous danger here with power of these stats functions.  Statistics builds upon assumptions and methods in a quick chain.  If you just jump to a particular formula without understanding all of what led you to use that formula, you may not appreciate the assumptions nor be as able to change approaches when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><category term="Harvard" /><category term="R" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Spyder" /><category term="Jupyter" /><summary type="html">Yay!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rodeo - First Impressions</title><link href="/rodeo/2017/12/28/Rodeo-First-Impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rodeo - First Impressions" /><published>2017-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rodeo/2017/12/28/Rodeo-First-Impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rodeo/2017/12/28/Rodeo-First-Impressions/">&lt;p&gt;OK… I’m starting to &lt;strong&gt;use&lt;/strong&gt; Rodeo, not just toy with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized there was no “Project” functionality yet.  But it seemed really odd that there was no way to
set the current working directory so it was connected to the location of the file.  This isn’t a bug,
though some have argued the case on GitHub.  It just takes getting used to.  You just use the directory
chooser of the console pane to get where you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That felt like a negative.  But if so, it’s easily outweighed by a huge benefit - the editor has &lt;em&gt;vim&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;emacs&lt;/em&gt; bindings!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the IDE that’s been giving me the most grief has been RStudio.  That sucker core dumps if
just breathe funny.  And it’s weird.  For some projects, it just works fine.  For others, SOMETHING
repeatably crashes it.  The trouble is that it’s repeatable for a period.  Something in the environment
is such that R crashes.  But when that environment thing isn’t there, RStudio is fine.  That sort of
problem is devilishly difficult to chase or report.  It seems there’s something related to the Clipboard
that’s at play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm… or… it actually seems dependent on what is being pasted.  It seems to be most common when
pasting a command that involves reading/accessing a file and the filepath is invalid.  But…  it is
oddly not 100% repeatable.  It will eventually do it it without crashing.  It is weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But…back to Rodeo.  It sort of grows on you.  I &lt;strong&gt;like&lt;/strong&gt; the vim binding but I keep forgetting it’s
there because I’m bouncing between so many things.  In a lot of ways, though, it seems a work in progress.
I’ve seen some folk comment they don’t want to see it become bloated like Spyder.  I had to chuckle.
I didn’t consider Spyder bloated at all.  Have these guys used Komodo or Eclipse?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Rodeo" /><category term="Python" /><category term="RStudio" /><summary type="html">OK… I’m starting to use Rodeo, not just toy with it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Swirling Round and Round</title><link href="/project/swirlypy/2017/12/23/Swirling-Round-and-Round/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Swirling Round and Round" /><published>2017-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/swirlypy/2017/12/23/Swirling-Round-and-Round</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/swirlypy/2017/12/23/Swirling-Round-and-Round/">&lt;p&gt;I just stumbled atop a couple things that may prove helpful or may just be an entertaining distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working through a MOOC that uses R.  SInce the upcoming Bootcamp is exclusively Python, I’m mirroring the work in Python.  But to follow along I need to learn R.  I’d been bouncing in and out of Swirl to get what I needed for the moment (kinda in a “I know what need, these concepts aren’t new to me… I just need to know your syntax, silly tutorial program!”).  Swirl asks at the beginning if you want the tutorial or the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/swirldev/swirl_courses&quot;&gt;Swirl repository&lt;/a&gt;”.  I’d glanced at it before.  But this morning I actually looked at it.  And dear heavens if it isn’t a slew of stuff parallel to a lot of these Stats and Data Science courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… given my current focus on mirroring R and Python work, I just had to scratch a curiosity and sure enough I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alexander-bauer/swirlypy&quot;&gt;Swirlypy&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ll have to play with this.  Many people who’ve been pining for something like this seem to want a basic Python tutorial.  The structure and program is here but the library seems empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How hard would it be to port the R swirl courses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright.  I’ve got a slightly better sense of the scope of the task.  First, this is how to run things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step one - get the package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$SOMEDIR&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git clone https://github.com/alexander-bauer/swirlypy
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in python…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SOMEDIR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;swirlypy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Full path to location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;swirlypy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;course&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;course&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Course&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;load&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;COURSEDIR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repostiory comes with a sample courses.  So I just did “SOMEDIR/swirlypy/courses/intro”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works, after a fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a ton of similarity between this and swirl.  The courses are YAML files for both.  The general structure is similar.  The challenge is the types of questions supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems swirl itself is not that old.  The effort to create swirlypy started almost immediately after the start of swirl.  But development of swirlypy stopped and swirl went another year or so of active development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be insane… but I want to take  a crack at this.  It would be good practice with git, matplotlib and stats stuff in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I’ve set up rpy2, it probably wouldn’t be wise to depend on R directly like this.  When using the data sets, these can be found online such has &lt;a href=&quot;https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grabbed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/swirldev/swirl_courses&quot;&gt;the Swirl Courses&lt;/a&gt; respository.  Let’s try to port what’s listed there as “Overview of Statistics”.  And… because it’ll be a huge focus of the next few months, let’s try to incorporate pandas in even this simple data analysis…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;chdir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;getcwd&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;chdir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;swirl_courses/Open_Intro/Overview_of_Statistics&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'grep &quot;^- Class&quot; *yaml'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;universal_newlines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DataFrame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to_replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'- Class: '&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;regex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value_counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;                   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;58&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt;                 &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd_question&lt;/span&gt;           &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mult_question&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exact_question&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;video&lt;/span&gt;                   &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;range_question&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text_order_question&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text_many_question&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt;                    &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text_question&lt;/span&gt;           &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe many of those will be straightforward extensions of classes already built in swirlypy.  The real challenge and the high runner is &lt;em&gt;figure&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may start with some of the easier ones to get going.  Text out to be a straight drop in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More later…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Swirl" /><category term="SwirlyPy" /><category term="R" /><category term="Python" /><summary type="html">I just stumbled atop a couple things that may prove helpful or may just be an entertaining distraction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stats Series</title><link href="/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/22/Stats-Series/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stats Series" /><published>2017-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/22/Stats-Series</id><content type="html" xml:base="/training/ph_525_series/2017/12/22/Stats-Series/">&lt;p&gt;It’s time to shift gears a bit.  I need to start &lt;em&gt;using&lt;/em&gt; this blog, not just play with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve about a month left before starting the &lt;strong&gt;Metis Data Science Bootcamp&lt;/strong&gt;.  One of the things I’d slotted to do in December was to work through this online course series from Harvard.  The Metis Boocamp is exclusively Python.  A number of these MOOCs and books focus on R.  I have found one book that does both Python and R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this course, I’m going to try to replicate work in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harvard course is a 6 part series that parallels the book &lt;em&gt;Data Analysis for the Life Sciences&lt;/em&gt;.  I was drawn to the series when searching for a refresher on Linear Algebra.  That’s course 2 of 6.  I chose to use HackerRank for the Linear Algebra review and will now push through the entire Harvard series, time permitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course starts with the R tutorial.  In order to load packages, I had to back out and load some more stuff in Anaconda:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;conda install gcc_linux-64
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;conda install gxx_linux-64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was able to proceed with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-R highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;swirl&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;rafalib&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first exercise in PHP 525.1x is a “First Assessment: Run Swirl Exercises”.  It’s essentially a quiz on basics of R syntax which you get through &lt;em&gt;swirl&lt;/em&gt; - the R tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used RStudio for swirl.  But then I fired up two parallel Jupyter notebooks - one for R and another for Python.  I installed &lt;a href=&quot;https://rpy2.bitbucket.io/&quot;&gt;rpy2&lt;/a&gt; and was even able to call the “version” command from Python to confirm the version of R.  But the main benefit of this was the access the standard datasets in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fairly strongly encouraged an approach of projects in RStudio.  I will try to mirror that in Python.  This should be a good chance to test out both Rodeo, which seems most akin to RStudio and Spyder.  The questions for this next exercise seem simple enough that notebooks will still work fine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><category term="Harvard" /><category term="R" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Rodeo" /><category term="Spyder" /><summary type="html">It’s time to shift gears a bit. I need to start using this blog, not just play with it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog Toddler Steps - Step 03</title><link href="/blog/2017/12/22/Blog-Toddler-Steps-03/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog Toddler Steps - Step 03" /><published>2017-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/12/22/Blog-Toddler-Steps-03</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/12/22/Blog-Toddler-Steps-03/">&lt;p&gt;Exploring how to work Jekyll to accomplish what I want with this site…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of things aren’t really necessary at the moment.  Nonetheless, I need to start getting my feet wet putting some of these things together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seem to be many ways of doing any one thing.  Furthermore, some of these plugins seem small or trivial enough that it would be just as easy just to toss in the couple files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with &lt;em&gt;jekyll-category-pages&lt;/em&gt;.  In order to use these plugins or make these changes, it’s rather important to understand how Jekyll functions at all.  Problem with lots of these plugins or plugin like things is there’s no fully functional demo.  This one does show a listing of categories.  But it’s not a format I’d want.  If what I want is paginated category pages…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would seem I could… just… build upon or extend the current functionality I have with HydeJack.  Jekyll isn’t clearly modular.  You have to take care when adding or changing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… it &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; looks like it would be simple to change a couple of lines in a layout file to get pagination for categories.  But it doesn’t work… which is why someone went and made that plugin.  The “correct” thing these days is to upgrade to &lt;em&gt;jekyll-paginate-v2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK.  Upgraded.  But the next problem is figuring out &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; to use this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT -  Thu Dec 21 16:36:07 CST 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brushed up on Ruby.  But ironically, learning the &lt;strong&gt;syntax&lt;/strong&gt; of Ruby doesn’t help so much when your problem is in packaging and file management.  I picked up where I left off.  At least I was better equipped to do web searches for solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble was I just dumped the Gem into the &lt;em&gt;_includes&lt;/em&gt; directory which is where Jekyll docs says plugins go.  The files were getting pulled in.  But not in the appropriate order which was leading to dependency gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A working solution needs follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://newcome.wordpress.com/2013/02/07/hacking-on-local-ruby-gems/&quot;&gt;this sort of approach&lt;/a&gt;.  Sure enough, changing the site’s Gemfile from&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gem&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;jekyll-paginate-v2&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gem&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;jekyll-paginate-v2&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;_local/jekyll-paginate-v2&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;was all  I needed to switch to a local copy of the gem so I could play and explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picking up &lt;a href=&quot;http://pryrepl.org/&quot;&gt;pry&lt;/a&gt; along the way…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK.  That very much helped.  I could see what was happening.  Or more specifically what wasn’t happening.  Jekyll has some oddities baked in given its evolution.  Things that look similar in the templating are treated differently under the hood.  To add to the difficulty, the HydeJack theme does something interesting with categories.  It creates a collection for the categories you bother to document.  This is “featured” categories.  The &lt;em&gt;jekyll-paginate-v2&lt;/em&gt; has “autopages” which tries to autogenerate these sorts of pages.  I did &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; like that.  I settled on changing HydeJack as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Upgrade” to paginate-v2.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Switch the “featured_categories” collection to “no output”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Symlink a category directory to “featured_categories”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not this works just fine.  With Hydejack and these “featured” collections, I only get the link this indexing for the tages and categories I deem important enough.  With paginate-v2 I get some extra functionality, including a “trail”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the trail, I have to play around with CSS to get it to look good…  Tweaked the templating a bit too.  Looks good.  Now to prep things and deploy it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm… running into issues…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody’s fascinated with  &lt;a href=&quot;https://yoast.com/slug/&quot;&gt;slugs&lt;/a&gt; these days…  There’s some inconsistency between urls here.  Jekyll doesn’t seem to be honoring defined slugs.  No that’s not the problem.  The trouble is parts of Jekyll are honoring things case-senstive and other parts of Jekyll force things to lower case.  Some people have just modifed Jekyll’s source to change that behavior.  That doesn’t seem good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… I don’t like it.  But any “fix” I implement here would be kludgey.  It’s probably safer long term to submit to case insenstive… sigh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… back to slugs…  HydeJack is using the slug parameter to connect the category to the &lt;em&gt;featured_category&lt;/em&gt; collection.  So, ironically, it does need to remain case sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… I’ve gotten my feet wet with Jekyll plugins and modifying things through the Liquid templating.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Ruby" /><category term="Liquid" /><summary type="html">Exploring how to work Jekyll to accomplish what I want with this site…</summary></entry></feed>