<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2018-01-17T06:38:34+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Joseph Hamilton - Solution Oriented Data Scientist</title><subtitle>A website by and for Joseph Hamilton. A place to explore projects and pursuits, to chase curiosities and catch dreams.
</subtitle><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Saved by Snapshots</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/16/Saved-By-Snapshots/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saved by Snapshots" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/16/Saved-By-Snapshots</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/16/Saved-By-Snapshots/">&lt;p&gt;Guess what… I’ve &lt;strong&gt;already&lt;/strong&gt; benifitted from setting up a snapshot regimen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup.  That didn’t take long.  I made a global subsitute in a file where I should have specified
only the lines after the cursor.  I didn’t realize what I’d done.  But I was making blogging changes
with Jekyll in update mode.  So I could &lt;strong&gt;see&lt;/strong&gt; I’d screwed something up immediately but I couldn’t
tell what.  And attempting to undo it didn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick peek into the snapshots directory and it became clear I’d screwed up the YAML header stuff.
Again… YAML is &lt;strong&gt;PICKY&lt;/strong&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved having this many years ago on Solaris.  So I knew of the benefit of having it.  And I imagined
I’d need it to protet myself from myself.  I didn’t expect to need it so soon.  :grin:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Guess what… I’ve already benifitted from setting up a snapshot regimen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Benson - Data Exploration 01</title><link href="/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-X01/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Benson - Data Exploration 01" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-X01</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-X01/">&lt;p&gt;Project Benson - Data Exploration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the link below to a Jupyter Notebook encapsulating my initial Data Exploration related to Project Benson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes some investigation, some chaos, some play, some fun, etc.  Working towards what techniques
may work for our overall project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/joseph-r-hamilton/Project_Benson/blob/master/Exploration/Project%20Benson%20-%20Exploration%2001.ipynb&quot;&gt;Project Benson - Exploration 01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project Benson - Data Exploration</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Benson Begins</title><link href="/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-Begins/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Benson Begins" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-Begins</id><content type="html" xml:base="/project/benson/2018/01/16/Project-Benson-Begins/">&lt;p&gt;Project Benson has begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow.  We hit the ground running alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day of the bootcamp and we’re busy on the first project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projets throughout the Metis Bootcamp seem to trend in a couple of ways.  One trend is from a group
effort to a solo effort.  For this first project, my partners in crime are Dean, Derrick and Kendall.
We sequestered ourselves at the sunny side of the floorspace and barricaded ourselves from the rest of
the world as we discussed how best to attack the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kendall and I were the first to find the data.  But we found it in different places.  And it’s good that
we did so.  The &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.mta.info/developers/download.html&quot;&gt;MTA site&lt;/a&gt; provides the data in smaller
chunks, which should prove more amenable to rapid prototyping.  But as Kendall dug into the data available
on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.ny.gov/&quot;&gt;New York site&lt;/a&gt; site, we realized it was the same data, same columns, but…
the data was available in entirety, millions of rows of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We chatted about what to look for… or how to use the data available.  Did we care about location down
the level of which street exit of any particular station?  Should we focus on Spring traffic since the
problem statement suggested an event at the start of Summer?  Dare we try to accommodate or consider
the effect of Spring Break?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the data enough to realize we had some data munging to do so we clearly needed something
in the fashion of people per unit time at any station while the turnstile data is just reporting a
(supposedly) ever increasing count of the actual turnstile reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We broke with the idea that we should first play with the data more and then we could scale or filter
as we chose.  Furthermore, Dean stated he would attempt to work in Tableau since he had access to that.
This is one of those benefits to the group aspect of the Metis Bootcamp.  We all bring different things
to the table and can share and learn from one another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Project Benson has begun.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootcamp - Day One</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/16/Bootcamp-Day-One/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootcamp - Day One" /><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/16/Bootcamp-Day-One</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/16/Bootcamp-Day-One/">&lt;p&gt;Bootcamp has begun!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realize I’ve not yet published a post describing the Metis Bootcamp, or my motivations for pursuing
colloboration wtih Metis to jump into a career in Data Science.  I may have to get to that soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m starting this post while Alice is lecturing about command line.  A fair amount of the first week
is going to be somewhat old hat for me.  So I should have lots of bandwidth to do other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is a bit of an illusion.  The instructors (David and Alice) actually discussed this earlier
in their introductory presentations.  They fully expect that each and every one of us will hit a wall
at some point in the bootcamp.  It just will be different for each person.  I believe for me it will
be at about the third week.  That’s because we all can see the curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bootcamp starts with the basics.  This is largely because all of us are coming from different
backgrounds.  Many of us will have different sets of strengths and weaknesses.  We could see this
after all the introductions.  It’s a fascinating mix.  I seem to be the only one coming from a
telecommunications industry background.  There are some “things” that seem to be represented by
more than one person, like Psychology, Economics.  There’s one person who is a former recruiter.
There’s another who actually is coming from a Data Analytics background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… thing are going to shift into warp speed rather soon.  They repeated the concept there there
will be a “core” set of things that we repeat and stress and will be expected to “master”.  But the
bootcamp also covers a sufficient amount of things in a broad overview fashion such that pretty much
nobody can master everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next… we’re all coming in with slightly different laptop configurations.  The suggested thing is
MacOS.  I’m using Linux in a Virtual Machine on top of Windows.  Kendall has a Windows laptop and
has installed an Unbuntu app.  I had to look into that.  Apparently, Microsoft and Ubuntu have
colloborated to put an app in the Windows App Store which is accessible for Windows 10.  What you
end up with is something like a Docker container to provide you with a Linux shell.  It doesn’t
seem to support a GUI.  So… it seems to be something like Cygwin on steroids… or more appropriately
a real Linux… but only the shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may not need this now… especially since I have a robust VM.  But this is interesting nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also just learned about “NerdTree” - a plugin for vim.  I’m so much an old-timer that when Amy
asked me if I used “vim” it didn’t register to me… because I know it as “Vee-Eye”.  But to be honest
I DO use vi rather tham vim or gvim.  But I may have try this one.  I may not feel it as a “need”
so much because I’m just so used to using vi without this.  But I believe this is what I’ve seen
others using on the train.  And it’s not just that this plugin shows the directory structure…
it shows git status as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what’s fun about this sort of group experience… learning from each other all the nifty
things and tricks that are out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the start of actual instruction, today involved several introdoction presentations.
Nathan (Program Manager) explained policies (attendance policy?!?  &lt;strong&gt;grades&lt;/strong&gt; ?!?).  Ashley (Career Advisor)
went over the support Metis provides overall to assist with the Career Support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the interesting aspect of this bootcamp.  Metis is very focused on placement.  The Metis
bootcamp is audited.  Their auditor does require employment/placement tracking.  This seems rather
different from the training provided via WorkNet… where the junior colleges or universities don’t do
this so much and even WorkNet may be more focused on ensuring you get any external certification tied
to that course.  As such, quite literally the Metis Bootcamp may be viewed as a Career Placement effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More instruction and then eventually we formed groups and began work on the first project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Bootcamp has begun!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stats Series - Course Two Wrapup</title><link href="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/15/Course-Two-Wrapup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stats Series - Course Two Wrapup" /><published>2018-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/15/Course-Two-Wrapup</id><content type="html" xml:base="/training/ph_525_series/2018/01/15/Course-Two-Wrapup/">&lt;p&gt;Finished with Course Two!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have finished the second course in the Harvard series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve given some thought with regards to “what next”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I consider this course series and the book it’s tied to is a very worthwhile experience
overall.  Nonetheless, I’m not entirely certain this was what I expected or that it met my needs
with regards to a refresher on Linear Algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not get “past” where I’d gotten with my earlier work on HackerRank.  But I certainly went deeper. 
Furthermore, I got a better grounding in how to connect this sort of regression overall to basic
statistics.  And this certainly showed how to use this relative to experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the entire thing.  This whole Harvard series is focused on this one aspect of using statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I fall back and compare the context of this text and course series relative to the Metis Bootcamp
curriculum I can easily see a difference between depth and breadth.  Then when I compare the Metis Bootcamp
curriculum to the broad overview of Data Science topics in general, I can see that even that is but a sampling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… I’m going to pause entirely on the Harvard series for a while.  Instead, I’m going to focus on the
topics covered by the Bootcamp while pushing through a couple other textbooks in the background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><category term="Harvard" /><summary type="html">Finished with Course Two!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootcamp - Final Prep</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/15/Bootcamp-Final-Prep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootcamp - Final Prep" /><published>2018-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/15/Bootcamp-Final-Prep</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/15/Bootcamp-Final-Prep/">&lt;p&gt;Just one last day before the bootcamp begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve more or less attained what I’d set out to do to prepare.  I finished the first two courses
in the Harvard series.  I’ve brought the blog to a point where it will serve me during the bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There remains any number of things I could have done.  But the time is up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I’ve been tackling a number of normal life things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also backed up the virtual machine I’m using for the bootcamp in a low-tech manner.  I simply copied
the entire thing to a USB stick.  This is the 3rd level of what I implemented.  I’ve got an rsync set to
run daily to dump to another part of the host storage.  I’ve got similar timers to give me period
snapshots.  Next, I’ve got a timer to backup to the cloud.  I plan to copy to the USB stick on a weekly
basis.  All of this should keep me from too much delay from anything from shooting myself in the foot
to theft of the laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point on, it’s just time to jump on in and roll with things.  I’l looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Just one last day before the bootcamp begins.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Last Dry Run</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/12/Last-Dry-Run/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Last Dry Run" /><published>2018-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/12/Last-Dry-Run</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/12/Last-Dry-Run/">&lt;p&gt;I have been working at the Metis site today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I caught an earlier train immediately after dropping my daughter off at high school.  It is still rather close
and depends on finding parking and walking to the train stop in time.  But that’s the express train.  It is
actually about two-thirds the travel time.  If I miss that one, the next available train should get me
down here in time before things start for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night I caught a curiosity.  I find a remark that a particular event shouldn’t be deemed terribly
noteworthy because it’s still within the customary 5% confidence level.  That seemed like something I could
try to replicate.  I continued that effort today.  For a while I was conviced the comment was wrong
because the significance seemed much greater.  The trouble was that I had missed an implicit assumption
about the data table I was reading.  I replicated the work properly and had to agree with the comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was good about this endeavor, this curiosity, was that I was able to go “out there” and find the
data and bring it back through data cleaning, munging, through Pandas and use the same techniques I’ve
been learning in these MOOCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of thing I foresee we’ll be doing a lot in this Metis Bootcamp.  Take the techniques
and go out in the wild to see what fun we can have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the actual instructors are down here.  They’re working through their overall plans since it will
be a team taught experience.  I had a bit of time to talk.  But like Wednesday, I’m not really supposed
to be here.  So when or if they leave, I’ll have to pack up and head out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made good progress in the MOOC.  I should have no problem finishing up the second course before
the bootcamp.  But I may not be able to keep up even a slowed pace on the next two courses.  David (one
of the instructors) was rather skeptical of that idea.  No worries.  The main idea behind the Harvard
series was to prepare me for the bootcamp.  If the bootcamp demands preempts it, this will be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent work in this MOOC was interesting.  I had to learn a new Python module as I mirror the
work.  The module is patsy.  It was rather specifically built to mimic or match the functionality
in R.  But… it is slightly different enough to have given me a bit of work to understand it.  The
interesting thing is apparently there are some ways it improved upon the behavior in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are a couple of things for this dry run that are simply different from previous trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could I have truly tested the main experiences of the commute if I didn’t do of the typical
commuter things?  It’d be like going to the Alps and not any skiing.  Or going to South Africa and
visiting no wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What experience have I been avoiding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the laptop while on the train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I am not certain I’ll be doing more if it.  I’ve seen folk doing it.  Maybe I’ll be more
like everyone else when I have stuff I want to wrap up or explore.  But, you just end up being so
cramped and squished.  But I’ve proven it in, so to speak.  I’m typing this up as others board the
train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing is that this was the first time I’m returning in the same pattern as I’ll be doing
for the next few weeks.  I made the walk in 18 minutes.  Doable at a fast clip.  But pointless.
There’s an oddity with the train schedules.  There are lots of trains outbound between five and six.
But half or more have express segments, passing many stops including mine.  If I don’t get on a train
shortly after 5, the next viable one is at about a quarter to six.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I have been working at the Metis site today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog Adolescence</title><link href="/blog/2018/01/11/Blog-Adolescence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog Adolescence" /><published>2018-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2018/01/11/Blog-Adolescence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2018/01/11/Blog-Adolescence/">&lt;p&gt;The blog has a new front door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have spent more time on this than I should have.  But it was worthy as an expereince of learning
more about Jekyll, Liquid, SCSS/SASS, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did upgrade to HydeJack Pro to quickly gain some templates for projects.  This provided me a few other
things to consider using.  One of those was sort of natural.  When I started the blog, it was pretty much
just a blog.  I hadn’t yet developed collections or projects, etc.  But once you create a showcase for
Projects, then what is your website?  Should it start folk in the blog and they can then bounce to the
projects?  Or vice versa?  The Hydejack solution is a Welcome page which permits you to select and
highlight a few projects and blog posts.  It’s sort of a “all of the above” answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I went searching for what others had done after trying Hydejack, I saw some other themes in
action.  Indeed, I came across a &lt;a href=&quot;https://rcabanasdepaz.github.io/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;large&lt;/strong&gt; listing of Jekyll themes&lt;/a&gt;.
I also found a different approach I liked.  This was the Jekyll-Uno theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… I only wanted that one aspect of Jekyll-Uno - the clean, austere front-door.  So, at the very
least I had to determine how to tack on just that part yet have it integrated well enough with the rest.
Furthermore, Hydejack actually provided better functionality for what to put on that front page.  I didn’t
just want to tack on something extra.  I really had to merge and blend things together.  That’s the part that
was a good working experience in Liquid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it works well enough, though it may be a bit ugly under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the framework and functionality of the blog should be ready to suit my needs.  And none too
soon since the Metis Bootcamp is just days away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Jekyll Liquid" /><summary type="html">The blog has a new front door.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dry Run Report</title><link href="/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dry Run Report" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report</id><content type="html" xml:base="/metis/2018/01/10/Dry-Run-Report/">&lt;p&gt;I have journeyed to downtown Chicago today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be joining the 2018 Winter Cohort of the Metis Data Science Bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual activities begin next Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seemed very prudent to make a number of dry run commutes to work out the kinks.  I’ve been collaborating with Metis for a couple months now
in the sense that I’ve been coming to their facility for a number of meetups and events.  For all of that I simply drove.  Driving to/from Chicago
in rush hour times is a rather undesirable task, but the real kicker is the expense for parking.  To pay the evening rate for an evening meetup is
a lot different than paying every day for a full day’s parking.  In a real sense a car in downtown Chicago is a liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually came down last Friday.  I made that a leisurely affair.  I left shortly before noon.  I brought my young son… who actually helped because he was familiar with mini-DisplayPort adapters.  I haven’t needed to use that sort of connector between laptops and monitors before.  After an our or so playing around with basics of hooking up to the network and external monitors and whatnot, we returned.  Again, it was at our leisure.  We popped into a number of stores along the way back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m trying to match real times.  And (as I kind of expected) I missed my train.  It took a lot longer to find parking at the train station which was also a lot further away.  I thought it was far away last time.  Sheesh!!  But that’s why I’m doing these dry runs.  Nathan, the Metis Chicago Program Manager informs me this cohort will be changing the schedule a bit.  So Friday, I’ll actually take a different train and attempt to get get here by 9am.  Nobody may be here.  Again, there’s no reason for anyone to be here at the moment.  But if so, I’ll just pop on over to UIC and work from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve plopped myself down at a workstation.  I may pick up an adapter to be able to use more than one external monitor.  I’ll be continuing work on the blog and the MOOC I’m pursuing… at least till Nathan boots me out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I have journeyed to downtown Chicago today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog Enhancements</title><link href="/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog Enhancements" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2018/01/10/Blog-Enhancements/">&lt;p&gt;I took a brief pause between the first and second courses in this Harvard series to take another look
at a couple of things.  One of the things I need to wrestle with quickly is how to handle projects on
this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I’m using the HydeJack theme.  I could upgrade to the Pro version to get some additional
support for projects.  But I’m not certain I want that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went off on a journey on the web to see how others are using Hydejack or Jekyll in general for projects.
I found a ton of orphaned sites.  Lots of people seem to be starting or barely starting blogs and then
abandoning them.  I may have said earlier, but I find this blog is actually primarily for &lt;strong&gt;ME&lt;/strong&gt;.  If
others are reading this, that’s great.  And this does serve as a bit of a showcase.  But I know from
experience the value of being able to look backwards at logs, journals, etc., of your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I’ve also found very little really effective use of these project sections, tabs, pages or whatnot.
But I did find a few.  So I have to ponder what I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also reminded I need to go back and fluff out tags and categories.  They end up a bit “messy” in
the site layout if I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also reviewed the blogs created by the 2017 Fall Cohort of the Metis Bootcamp.  These were &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt;
project-centric actually.  Maybe I’m just chatty.  But again, experience has taught me that it’s actually
very valuable to be able to look backwards after several months and years to see exactly what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there really does seem to be a fairly consistent pattern here of portraying projects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a front-page of sorts which either uses a picture and one-liner for each project as a link to a more robust page for that project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each project is summarized as a single page which is essentially a summary of the overall project with a focus on the results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some pages includes links to the previous and next projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some folk used the blog as their mechanism to portray their projects.  But then the blog served almost no other purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what do I want?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at some of the better examples I’ve found using Hydejack Pro…  I found one that rather easily
incorporated links between the (single) post and the project page.  I could do almost the same thing using
a dedicated category page.  In the interest of time, I probably should just upgrade.  I likely won’t take
advantage of everything in Pro.  I’ve found an “Intro” I like better.  I only hesitate because I’d probably
benefit more from building my own stuff in Jekyll.  But I know full well that could eat up a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to move quickly here.  Before the Metis Bootcamp starts, I would like to have back-created a page and some posts related to a project I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time passes…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK.  I’m now halfway through the second course and taking some time to work on the blog.  For the purpose
of working in the project functionality, I elevated the previous post on SwirlyPy to a project.  I &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; hope to
keep working on that till it works well enough to serve my needs and help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chasing this I found some eye-candy I also want.  But… I’ve reached a point where I have what I want with
regards to the project pages connecting to and from the related blog posts.  So, I’m pushing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joseph Hamilton</name><email>hamilton.joseph.r@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Projects" /><summary type="html">I took a brief pause between the first and second courses in this Harvard series to take another look at a couple of things. One of the things I need to wrestle with quickly is how to handle projects on this blog.</summary></entry></feed>